welcome to meditating with john vervicky
we live stream every morning every
weekday morning at 9 30 a.m if you're
joining us for the first time don't be
put off by this
uh this is a dharma day in which i'm
teaching a new lesson
we met we meet on mondays and sometimes
sometimes wednesdays also friday but
every monday every alternative monday
we do a dharma day in which i teach a
new lesson we alternate that with papaya
day in which
i review the whole ecology practices one
the prior day is
from the eastern wisdom traditions
buddhism and taoism the practices
uh we have cultivated from those
traditions and then
the next opera day is from the western
wisdom traditions epicureanism
platonism we're going through the wisdom
of hypatia right now and going through
the practices for cultivating wisdom
drawn from the epicurean tradition
so if you're here for meditating don't
worry please see the description
and find links uh to previous lessons
and sits do
lesson one which will start you on the
core four of mindfulness
try to do uh one or two lessons every
week
keep meeting with us and you'll
integrate very quickly with the course
and with the sangha please help me
help as many people as possible by
liking this video stream
to raise its profile on the youtube
algorithm
um we at the end we
will generally have a q a although uh
sometimes for time reasons we don't get
much of a chance for that
for those questions um please limit them
to the ecology of practice
you get priority on tuesdays and
thursdays two questions concerning the
uh practices gone from the eastern
traditions monday wednesday and friday
drawn from the western edition classes
on monday wednesday and friday
tend uh to be a bit longer usually going
45 minutes
classes on tuesdays and 30 tuesdays and
thursdays
going about 30 to 35 minutes so let's
begin let's get let's get going
so we're doing the epicureans and we're
we've zeroed in
and i reviewed a lot on friday
about the sets of practices and now
we're
zoning in um zeroing in on
the core practice which is philosophical
contemplative uh
companionships this is a way of
generating philosophical
fellowship within which we cultivate the
virtues and wisdom
together philia the fellowship love
of sophia wisdom failure sophia
contemplation uh fioria and remember is
these three things linked together
making
sense of the text because the practice
centers on a text
making sense of the text all right
making sense of
others the other people that you're
entering into fellowship with
and making sense with others
because all sense making is ultimately
done with and through
other people these
are all interconnected remember
contemplate hillary what's our basic
attitude
we are trying to travel far away from
the familiar
automatic our opinion our normal
egocentric
self and see something that we have not
seen before
seen something we have not seen before
okay so let's zero in first of all
network today we're moving more towards
the practice
so some practice principles
okay so making sense of the text
so what are what's the main couple of
main principles here
so thinking through the text
be by means of it and beyond it like
seeing through my glasses contemplation
thinking through the text not just
thinking about the text
or thinking at the text and what you're
doing is relating not only to the what
of the text the content of the text but
the how
of the text what do you mean about
relating to the how what you're
primarily doing here when you're making
sense of the text is you are trying
to adopt the perspective of the text
or more more personally the perspective
of the author of the text so let's say
it's plato
you're trying to adopt plato's
perspective
so think about doing this adverbially
what i'm trying to do is to see let's
say
the text is from plato i'm trying to see
through the text so i can see myself
other people the others in the group and
the world the situation when i want to
see it
platonically adverbially i don't i'm not
so much what i want to
i want to i it's
it's it's serious play i want to play as
if
as i'm reading the text listening to the
text
that that's actually me thinking
those words as if i'm plato thinking
those words
for the first time and what do i see
this is somewhat like lectio right how
do i see myself
and others and the world through this
text
so what i'm very much trying to do
right is i'm trying to engage in in
and visioning i want to see things
through the text the way the author of
the text
saw them as they were thinking those
thoughts
that's the goal you're here which is
very different from our normal goal
right our normal goal is to get to
understand as quickly as possible get it
just so that we can agree or disagree
evaluate judge we're putting aside
evaluating
judging stating our opinion and we are
opening up the contemplation opening up
and deepening that process
of really enacted understanding
of the text so that's the main thing
we're trying to do here
when we are trying to speak
in reference to the text what we're
trying to do is
invoke we're trying to give
voice
to the text speak from
the emerging presence
of the author of the text so as you
start to
see the text platonically you start to
get a sense
right of what it'd be like to be plato
speak from that
give voice to that you are and think
about
you're entering into a chorus a bunch of
people it's like there's been a piece of
music created called plato
and you're all singing it and the text
are the notes
that you're using to sing plato into
existence
it's very magical in the ritual sense of
the word magic
okay so that's the basic principle we're
trying to
envision and invoke envision and
invoke we're trying to see through the
text
adverbially
you might be asking where are we going
to get taxed and how big should it be
hang off on those practical questions
i'll answer those but let's get the
principles first
okay making sense of others so i won't
write that down you're just making sense
of others
what do we want to do here okay so here
the main thing is you're trying to
internalize other people
and you say what that means take their
perspective
but also let their words reverberate
and this is a good reverb reverberate
within you
try to create from mindfulness an inner
space of silence
away from that part of you that wants to
judge give opinions
react that states and let the words
reverberate in you
it's like it's like alexia listening you
want to let the words of other people
reverberate in you as much as possible
you want to see what their words
in conjunction with the text is like a
triangle here's their words
here's the words of the text and they
they sort of triangulate in on you and
they call something forth from you
then they write the there's something
so you're invoking plato but they're
evoking
from you okay evocation
so you're trying to have an evocative
response and you're triangulating
between
the words of the text and the words of
other people
let create a space it reverberate inside
of you
so that something is evoked in you
but what we're seeking here is to get
something to emerge from your depths
other than from the familiar center
of right your speaking mind
fioria so
evocation so we had
right first two we are envisioning
an invocation now we have
internalization and evocation
okay so again envisioning
when you're making sense of the text and
you're invoking
trying to right invoke the person i
invoke the
presence of plato sounds almost magical
um
and here right when we are making sense
of others
what we want to do is internalize them
by reverberating
and then evoking what's evoked from us
by from the words of the text and their
words
we create a silent space we reverberate
until something is evoked
from us so you're going to be speaking
at a much slower pace
than you normally do
okay making sense with others making
sense with others
okay so the thing to what you want to
think about here is the
the idea of coupled emergence
you're trying to couple with
the text and with others but especially
with the others
so that they're what's emerging from
them and what's emerging from you and
what's emerging from the text
are all coordinated coupled together
so here what we're trying to do is the
metaphor that's being used
consistently by the have and a reminder
that we're making use of this book
as well as a bunch of other books by
lahav
all right is resonate resonate
all these musical metaphors of course
and here what you're trying to do is
when
you are speaking and you're making sense
with others
this is incorporate incorporating
this literally means that we now think
of it as corporations
but originally goes back to the body of
christ
this is sharing one body we're trying to
co-embody
together so you speak and you're trying
to incorporate what other people have
said and what the text has said
so this is the opposite of what we
normally want to do normally we want to
distinguish ourselves look at me
and we want to distinguish ourselves
right from the text
and what people others have said this is
the opposite we're trying to incorporate
the text and what others have said and
so
another metaphor that's used all right
we'll have and many other people
is jazz right you're trying to pick up
on what other people have said
incorporate it into what you say add on
to it
vary it like in jazz where somebody
plays something
i pick up on it and then i play with it
and vary it and then pass it on to
somebody else
who picks up on picks up on it plays
with it
and passes it on so the main metaphor
you're doing here is we're trying as i
mentioned last time
we're trying to create a chorus of
voices all of us
each one of us is trying to give
voice to plato or to spinoza or to
kirkegaard
and we're creating a chorus of voices
together
all right now what does that mean what
are some things we shouldn't do
well here's what we shouldn't do don't
agree or disagree with the text if you
start agreeing
saying i agree or disagree you're not
doing this practice
okay don't evaluate it this is good this
is bad
okay three things to avoid you want to
avoid automaticity just
what does automaticity mean just
automatically i'm saying
you know quickly um acting
out of habit acting a lot of what is
familiar
acting out of speaking out of our normal
opinions so
we want to avoid automaticity we want to
avoid
autobiography avoid autobiography don't
give your anecdotes
don't relate this to your personal story
avoid
autobiography and then finally
avoid authority don't speak as an
authority on anything
because the author who is present is not
you not the other person it's the author
of the text
who is being presented present
presented and presented okay
so i want you to think of 3d
co-emergence what i mean by 3d
co-emergence
you're trying to get the depth of the
text
the depth of yourself
and the depth of others
you're trying to get these to all
mutually afford each other
3d co-emergence
if you get lahav not all of this is in
la have this is
me uh putting it together integrated
with epicureanness of integrating with
some cockside mnemonics
and ideas and also integrating it uh
with other practices i've done that are
similar to this
but so the 3d co-emergence that but this
is still this is
what this is going to the core of like
what i would argue bahave is trying to
get us to see he uses these words
it doesn't quite schematize it this way
but i think this is very
very consonant with his text depth of
the text depth of yourself
depth of others
okay so now the setup
how do we set this practice up
so you have a four by four he recommends
four to six all the work i've been doing
all the participants
this seems to be the golden number you
want four people who to agree to
agree to me at least a minimum of four
times
four people who agreed to meet and this
is going to be very much online
four times what you're going to do is
you're going to rotate the facilitator
each time it's a
different facilitator
what does the facilitator do okay so the
facilitator goes to agora this is a
website
it's uh www
dot filo practice
this is where at least start and then of
course with time there are other sources
dot org and there you will find a bunch
of
two paragraph readings philosophical
readings that have been chosen
to be specifically used in this practice
when you when everybody meets the
facilitator will organize the order when
you're meeting in person you can do it
spatially when you're meeting online
a good idea is to order people
alphabetically
and everybody remember who comes before
them and who comes after them
all right so organize the order
and the facilitator is going to lead
people through
the the sequence of uh of the meeting
the sequence of practices
okay so one of the things the first
thing the facilitator does is when
people meet
of course people are welcomed they're
greeted but the facilitator
basically tries to
reduce or prevent socializing do not
start
by socializing socialization comes after
people should greet each other but then
we should move immediately into the
practice that's actually highly
emphasized
in a couple places like because if
people get in
they get into this other mode and then
it actually
thwarts them getting into the the mode
we're trying to get into with this
practice
so plan to meet 60 to 90 minutes
okay so the sequences as i said
obviously the facilitator welcomes
everybody comes in
greets everybody right
and then what you want to do is you want
to
he he has a very much vague notion he
says do centering practices
i recommend setting up the core four of
mindfulness
find your centered all of you together
take some time
10 minutes or so find your center find
your route find your flow find your
focus
okay then you're going to do the main
exercise
which i will describe shortly
and then everybody does
so that's a four everybody does a
takeaway
what did they get from this and then
if people want you can go into
socializing
okay so that's the basic sequence
okay so let's talk about some basic
procedures these are
uh these are uh practices that you're
going to engage in regularly and
reliably that cultivate the skills
that you are going to be putting into
practice
as you do the main exercise okay so the
first
is slow reading
so the name is quite um explanatory
whenever the text is being read it's
usually as we'll see it's initially read
by the facilitator
the facilitator reads it slowly and
reads it in a lectio divina fashion
reads it in the sense of reciting it
the reader should pause periodically
throughout to
give people a time to a chance to
understand it
and and also a chance to start to
reverberate with it like in lexia
and so as i said here what you're trying
to do here is this is basically
you're trying to afford the reading is
trying to afford people
internalizing the text
starting to be able to envision it
right starting to be starting to be
preparing to invoke it
so that's the intent the slow reading
really this is take this seriously
this is also a way of bringing a
reverential attitude in
reverence doesn't mean i agree with this
or everything is true
reverence is this ha this is the
potential
of being profound
okay so the next is precious speaking
these are the halves names precious
speaking
okay so what are what so when you are
so let's talk first about the form of
your speech
you want condensed and focused speech
what's the principle i want to say as
much as possible
with as few words as possible i want to
say as much as possible
with as few words as possible and i
won't utter more than one
or maybe two sentences at most
okay what's the manner
the manner especially goes into that
point about resonating that resonance
metaphor
and here's where the previous epicurean
practices come in
speak and as you're speaking
you are savoring savoring your speech
you're opening yourself up silently to
all of these
associations and
you're also seeking various connections
between all those associations
you're not speaking that you're
conveying it you're
savoring savoring
savoring your speech that's why we've
practiced savoring so much
okay remember speak through the text
not at the text or about the text speak
through the text
fioria speak through the text
what you're trying to do is you are
trying to envision it you're trying to
invoke it
right you're trying to incorporate what
the text says what other people say
say into your speech okay
so speak through it not about it or at
it you are trying to
invoke whoever is like say augustine
and you're trying to speak through the
text as if
he was speaking through you
okay what about the content
of what you say as i said
you're trying to presence the author of
the text while incorporating what other
people say
presence the author of the text while
incorporating whether
people say you're trying to enter into
fellowship
right bring into the company of the
companionship
the author
so you're giving voice to the author
you're doing the coupled 3d emergence
you're trying to speak from depth to
depth
to depth and listen from depth to depth
to depth coupled
3d emergence
that's so that's slow reading and
precious speaking
third kind of procedure intentional
conversing
okay there's a
so when you're listening as i said
listen from the desk
try to create a space of silence within
letting things reverberate
savor what other people are saying
savor the text savor what other people
are saying
savor it savor the text this is why
we've practiced savoring so much
you are i like uh rusin's title of his
book
you are bearing witness to epiphany
you are bearing when so you're listening
to others you're bearing witness to
epiphany
like you are at a birth of a child
you're
bearing witness to it remember that
that's the original meaning of conceive
your concepts but now we're trying to
give birth
we're bearing witness we're giving birth
to plato or spinoza
or augustine and we're also giving birth
to ourselves
in coordination with that
so as i said when you're speaking
you speak from the depths
what it basically is here is extended
precious speaking
so you do the listening i just mentioned
so here now you're going to speak maybe
four
or five sentences max with
same form same manner
right so you do this very savoring
listening
like alexio davina listening and then
you do
when it's your turn to speak and people
are taking turns
you speak in an extended precious
speaking the facilitator makes sure
that people speak in turn according to
the order that was assigned
at the beginning
so as i said you're trying to speak so
and what the project is here is together
in a coordinated
cooperative coupled fashion we're trying
to co-presence
in an adverbial fashion the author of
the text the world
view of the text the way of seeing
things of that author
and that is calling from us and we're
calling to each other
to that
3d coupled co-emergence
okay so now what's the main exercise oh
sorry one more
one more sorry one more procedure
ruminatio
this is philosophical chanting
philosophical chanting
so the phyllis after the text has been
read and
the facilitator makes sure that
everybody has a basic understanding
the facilitator right chooses one
sentence
and then right you have sequential
chanting
one person chance it out chance out that
sentence
next person next person next person when
you're not
speaking and another person is chanting
you are accompanying them in your head
with silent recitation silent repetition
and you do that for a sequence you got
you can decide how long you want to do
it it's good to maybe do at least four
rounds
fours are good in these kinds of
practices
i recommend after each round
you also do a uh like a moment of
silence a pause
for people to recollect what has
happened
okay
now what we basically do in the main
exercise
is after people come in and greet
welcome we move to this
sequence of procedures this sequence of
procedures
slow reading
and two ruminatio
the philosophical chanting
three precious speaking
now the precious speaking
is in response to a question
it's analogous in some ways to
meditative questioning a good question
is something it
is something like what has the what is
the tech
what is not what has what is the text
provoking and evoking in you
what is the text provoking and invoking
in you
and everybody and again decide the
number of rounds you want to do this
everybody does precious speaking in
response to the question
precious speaking in response to the
provocative
evocative question
try to make it present oriented don't do
something like what does it mean to you
make it procedural perceptual what's
what's being evoked what's being
provoked in you
right now okay
then you move to a round of intentional
conversing
and then five the
away everybody in sequence spends a bit
of time
seeing what they're taking away from
the whole ritual that's it
that's how we do it that's how we engage
in philosophical contemplative
companionship
it's how we create the philia the
fellowship
of sophia of wisdom remember that sophia
always implies also
from these cysts and there's lots of
both sophia and promises going on here
okay so there's going to be a moment
we're going to adjust the camera
i'm going to sit together a short sit
again
do a brief chanting
and then we will go into the silent sit
i want to see where the trunk is
so everyone please get in position uh
set your phones on do not disturb
uh we will begin when i say begin we
will begin with a chance
a short chance and then we will go into
the silent set
begin
one
on
you get your silence set
so
slowly come out of your practice trying
as best you can to integrate what you
cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition character
by reciting the five promises to
yourself
so we're about at our time again today i
do promise
that we will do some extended q a
um tomorrow wednesday and friday we will
catch up with all of your questions
uh please uh be patient we're trying to
accommodate as much as we can
in the space and time that we have
available and remaining to us um i would
say to everybody uh please now if you
wish
you can go on and read the second to
begin reading the second degree of
wisdom
um in the wisdom of hypatia which is
about stoicism now we're moving to high
school
so everybody thank you for joining
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
uh please potentially join twitter
so you get the latest updates on the
stream invite others who might benefit
by sharing this series
uh join the discord server uh to do
extra sitting
movement practices uh we're gonna try
and form
a philosophical contemplative
companionships uh practice there
on the discord server there's just a lot
going on there i'll be on the discord
server tonight
for the general q a at 6 00 pm uh
eastern time
so please remember continuity of
practice is more important than sheer
quantity of practice
don't hold yourself to a standard of
harsh perfectionism
but virtuous friendship maybe virtuous
companionship
because there is no enemy within your
own mind and body there is no true
friend
ally companion on the path
greater than your own mind and body
relapse unto yourselves
and to each other i'll see you all
tomorrow take good care everyone